Brooklyn Museum
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Brooklyn Museum interviews of artists
1965-1968
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Brooklyn Museum
7 linear feet
Interviews of 72 artists, and transcripts for all but five, conducted by Arlene Jacobowitz, the Associate Curator for the Department of Painting and Sculpture at the Brooklyn Museum, between 1965 and 1968. The artists discuss their work in the museum collection. Also included are 38 edited excerpts of the interviews, approximately 2-3 min. in length, used as "audio-labels" in the 1968 "Listening to Pictures" installation at the museum.
Provenance
This collection was donated to the Archives of American Art by Dierdre Lawrence of the Brooklyn Museum in 1989.
Location of Originals
Almost all of the transcripts in this collection are photocopies. Original transcripts can be found in the Brooklyn Museum Libraries and Archives.
Related Material
The Brooklyn Museum Archives houses the records of the Departments of European Painting and Sculpture, American Painting and Sculpture, Contemporary Art (1897-2005), which contain records relating to the work of Arlene Jacobowitz.
Alternative Forms Available
All of the sound recordings in this collection were digitized for preservation and research access in 2009 and are available at the Archives of American Art offices.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Researchers may view the original reels for the archival notations on them, but original reels are not available for playback due to fragility.
Historical Note
The interview program at the Brooklyn Museum was begun by Arlene Jacobowitz in the spring of 1965 with artists whose works were on exhibition at the Brooklyn Museum. In 1968, excerpts from the interviews were incorporated into an exhibition entitled "Listening to Pictures," in which visitors could access the sound recordings using headphones while standing before the painting being discussed. The exhibition opened April 28, 1968, and was gradually disassembled, 1971-1973.
Scope and Content Note
Interviews of 72 artists, and transcripts for all but five, conducted by Arlene Jacobowitz, the Associate Curator for the Department of Painting and Sculpture, between 1965 and 1968. The artists discuss their work in the museum collection. Also included are 38 edited excerpts of the interviews, approximately 2-3 min. in length, used as "audio-labels" in the 1968 "Listening to Pictures" installation.
The artists interviewed are: Lennart Anderson, Stephen B. Antonakos, Marshall Arisman, Walter Barker, Leonard Baskin, Mary Bauermeister, Thomas Hart Benton, Isabel Bishop, Robert Brackman, Sydney Butchkes, Edmund Casarella, George Constant, Robert Warren Dash, Jose DeCreeft, Blanche Dombek, Tom Doyle, Jimmy Ernst, Neil Estern, Philip Evergood, Helen Frankenthaler, Jane Freilicher, Leon Goldin, Sidney Goodman, Sante Graziani, Balcomb Greene, John Grillo, William Gropper, Chaim Gross, Roy Gussow, Robert Gwathmey, Grace Hartigan, Edward Hopper, Nora Jaffe, Paul Jenkins, Minoru Kawabata, William Kienbusch, Karl Knaths, John Koch, Yayoi Kosama, Jennett Lam, Steven Lang, Robert Laurent, Jacob Lawrence, Jack Levine, Jacques Lipchitz, Seymour Lipton, Boris Margo, Ursula Meyer, Hans Moller, Walter Murch, Louise Nevelson, Toshio Odate, Elliot Offner, Douglas Ohlson, Kenzo Okada, Amanda Palmer, Irene Rice Pereira, Gabor Peterdi, Ad Reinhardt, Bill Richards, Larry Rivers, Emilio Sanchez, Karl Schrag, Ben Shahn, Charles Sheeler, Aaron Sopher, Moses Soyer, Raphael Soyer, William Thon, Albert Weinberg, and William and Marguerite Zorach.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as a single series:
Series 1: Interviews, 1965-1968 (Box 1-7; 7 lin. ft.)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Listening to pictures (1968-1973: Brooklyn Museum)
Subjects-Topical:
Artists -- United States -- Interviews; Art, American -- Exhibitions
Types of Materials:
Interviews; Transcripts
Names:
Anderson, Lennart, 1928-; Antonakos, Stephen, 1926-; Arisman, Marshall; Barker, Walter; Baskin, Leonard, 1922-2000; Bauermeister, Mary, 1934-; Benton, Thomas Hart, 1889-1975; Bishop, Isabel, 1902-; Brackman, Robert, 1898-; Butchkes, Sydney, 1922-; Casarella, Edmund, 1920-; Constant, George; Dash, Robert; De Creeft, José, 1884-; Dombek, Blanche, 1914-; Doyle, Tom; Ernst, Jimmy, 1920-1984; Estern, Neil, 1926-; Evergood, Philip, 1901-1973; Frankenthaler, Helen, 1928-; Freilicher, Jane, 1924-; Goldin, Leon, 1923-; Goodman, Sidney; Graziani, Sante, 1920-; Greene, Balcomb, 1904-1990; Grillo, John, 1917-; Gropper, William, 1897-; Gross, Chaim, 1904-; Gussow, Roy, 1918-; Gwathmey, Robert, 1903-1988; Hartigan, Grace; Hopper, Edward, 1882-1967; Jacobowitz, Arlene -- interviewer.; Jaffe, Nora; Jenkins, Paul, 1923-; Kawabata, Minoru, 1911-; Kienbusch, William, 1914-1980; Knaths, Karl, 1891-; Koch, John, 1909-; Kosama, Yayoi; Lam, Jennett, 1911-; Lang, Steven, 1944-1971; Laurent, Robert, 1890-1970; Lawrence, Jacob, 1917-; Levine, Jack, 1915-; Lipchitz, Jacques, 1891-1973; Lipton, Seymour, 1903-1986; Margo, Boris, 1902-; Meyer, Ursula, 1915-; Moller, Hans, 1905-; Murch, Walter; Nevelson, Louise, 1899-1988; Odate, Toshio; Offner, Elliot; Ohlson, Douglas Dean, 1936-; Okada, Kenzo, 1902-; Palmer, Amanda, 1931-; Pereira, I. Rice (Irene Rice), 1902-1971; Peterdi, Gabor; Reinhardt, Ad, 1913-1967; Richards, Bill, 1936-; Rivers, Larry, 1925-2002; Sanchez, Emilio, 1921-; Schrag, Karl; Shahn, Ben, 1898-1969; Sheeler, Charles, 1883-1965; Sopher, Aaron, 1905-1972; Soyer, Moses, 1899-1974; Soyer, Raphael, 1899-1987; Thon, William, 1906-; Weinberg, Albert; Zorach, Marguerite, 1887-1968; Zorach, William, 1887-1966
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Interviews, 1965-1968, Series 1:; (Box 1-7; 7 linear feet)
  This series contains interviews of 72 artists on 157 sound tape reels (1/4 in. tape). Jack Levine and John Koch were interviewed twice, so the collection contains 74 interviews total. Also found are brief excerpts of the interviews on 38 sound tape reels, made for the exhibition, "Listening to Pictures," an acoustiguide for a Walter Murch Retrospective exhibition on one sound tape reel, and a monologue by Elbert Weinberg on his painting, "Temptation of Eve" on one sound cassette. All interviews were conducted by Arlene Jacobowitz, Assistant Curator of Paintings and Sculpture at the Brooklyn Museum. Most of the interviews were recorded on one to three half-hour reels, except for the Ad Reinhardt and Walter Murch interviews, which are longer. Excerpts are typically between 2 and 3 minutes long. The interviews focus primarily on works by the artist that are in the museum's collection.
  As noted in the box inventory below, transcripts are available for all but five interviews, as well as for the Murch acoustiguide and the Weinberg monologue. The interviews without transcripts include that of Stephen Antonakos, Jane Freilicher, Seymour Lipton, Walter Murch, and Elbert Weinberg. The Edward Hopper interview has a transcript only, and no original sound recording or excerpt.
  Interviews, transcripts, excerpts, and other recordings are arranged alphabetically by interviewee.
  All of the sound recordings have been digitized for preservation and research access.
  - Lennart Anderson (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Original Interview, 1966 July 26, (1 sound tape reel)
    - Transcript, 1966
    - Excerpt, 1968, (1 sound tape reel)
  - Stephen Antonakos (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Original Interview, 1968 April 5, (2 sound tape reels)
  - Marshall Arisman (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Original Interview, 1968 March 21, (1 sound tape reel)
    - Transcript, 1968
    - Excerpt, 1968, (1 sound tape reel)
  - Walter Barker (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Original Interview, 1965 May 3, (1 sound tape reel)
    - Transcript, 1965
    - Excerpt, 1968, (1 sound tape reel)
  - Leonard Baskin (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Original Interview, 1968 January 29, (1 sound tape reel)
    - Transcript, 1968
    - Excerpt, 1968, (1 sound tape reel)
  - Mary Bauermeister (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
    - Original Interview, 1968 February 24, (2 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1968
    - Excerpt, 1968, (1 sound tape reel)
  - Thomas Hart Benton (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Original Interview, 1966 July 7, (2 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1966
  - Isabel Bishop (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Original Interview, 1965 May 3, (2 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1965
  - Robert Brackman (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Original Interview, 1966 July 12, (1 sound tape reel)
    - Transcript, 1966
  - Sydney Butchkes (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
    - Original Interview, 1967 June 22, (2 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1967
    - Excerpt, 1968, (1 sound tape reel)
  - Edmund Casarella (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Original Interview, 1966 May 18, (1 sound tape reel)
    - Transcript, 1966
  - George Constant (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Original Interview, 1965 April 29, (1 sound tape reel)
    - Transcript, 1965
  - Robert Warren Dash (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Original Interview, 1966 May 18, (1 sound tape reel)
    - Transcript, 1966
    - Excerpt, 1968, (1 sound tape reel)
  - José DeCreeft (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
    - Original Interview, 1966 May 18, (3 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1966
  - Blanche Dombek (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
    - Original Interview, 1966 September 21, (2 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1966
    - Excerpt, 1968, (1 sound tape reel)
  - Tom Doyle (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
    - Original Interview, 1968 March 21, (2 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1968
    - Excerpt, 1968, (1 sound tape reel)
  - Jimmy Ernst (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
    - Original Interview, 1966 November 2, (2 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1966
    - Excerpt, 1968, (1 sound tape reel)
  - Neil Estern (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Original Interview, 1966 June 2, (2 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1966
  - Philip Evergood (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
    - Original Interview, 1966 May 18, (3 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1966
    - Excerpt, 1968, (1 sound tape reel)
  - Helen Frankenthaler (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
    - Original Interview, 1966 May 23, (2 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1966
    - Excerpt, 1968, (1 sound tape reel)
  - Jane Freilicher (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Original Interview, 1965 April 29, (1 sound tape reel)
    - Excerpt, 1968, (1 sound tape reel)
  - Leon Goldin (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Original Interview, 1965 April 29, (1 sound tape reel)
    - Transcript, 1965
    - Excerpt, 1968, (1 sound tape reel)
  - Sidney Goodman (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Original Interview, 1968 January 24, (1 sound tape reel)
    - Addendum, 1968 January 24, (1 sound tape reel)
    - Transcript, 1968
  - Sidney Goodman (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Excerpt, 1968, (1 sound tape reel)
  - Sante Graziani (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Original Interview, 1968 January 29, (1 sound tape reel)
    - Transcript, 1968
    - Excerpt, 1968, (1 sound tape reel)
  - Balcomb Greene (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
    - Original Interview, 1966 December 14, (2 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1966
    - Excerpt, 1968, (1 sound tape reel)
  - John Grillo (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
    - Original Interview, 1965, (2 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1965
    - Excerpt, 1968, (1 sound tape reel)
  - William Gropper (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Original Interview, 1965 April, (1 sound tape reel)
    - Transcript, 1965
  - Chaim Gross (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Original Interview, 1968 January 23, (1 sound tape reel)
    - Transcript, 1968
  - Roy Gussow (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
    - Original Interview, 1966 June 2, (2 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1966
    - Excerpt, 1968, (1 sound tape reel)
  - Robert Gwathmey (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Original Interview, 1966 September 29, (2 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1966
  - Grace Hartigan (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Original Interview, 1965 April 20, (2 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1965
    - Excerpt, 1968, (1 sound tape reel)
  - Edward Hopper (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Transcript, 1968
  - Nora Jaffe (Box 3, Folder 14-15)
    - Original Interview, 1967 June 14, (2 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1967
    - Excerpt, 1968, (1 sound tape reel)
  - Paul Jenkins (Box 3, Folder 16-17)
    - Original Interview, 1966 December 14, (2 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1966
    - Excerpt, 1968, (1 sound tape reel)
  - Minoru Kawabata (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Original Interview, 1968 January 19, (1 sound tape reel)
    - Transcript, 1968
    - Excerpt, 1968, (1 sound tape reel)
  - William Kienbusch (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Original Interview, 1968 April 6, (1 sound tape reel)
    - Transcript, 1968
    - Excerpt, 1968, (1 sound tape reel)
  - Karl Knaths (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
    - Original Interview, 1966 July 11, (2 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1966
    - Excerpt, 1968, (1 sound tape reel)
  - John Koch (Box 4, Folder 5-7)
    (2 interviews)
    - Original Interview, 1966 May 20, (1 sound tape reel)
    - Transcript, 1966
    - Original Interview, 1968 February 15, (2 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1968
    - Excerpt, 1968, (1 sound tape reel)
  - Yayoi Kusama (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Original Interview, 1968 January 19, (2 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1968
  - Jennett Lam (Box 4, Folder 9-11)
    - Original Interview, 1966 July 26, (2 sound tape reels)
    - Transcripts, 1968, 1969
      (In addition to the photocopied transcript produced by the Brooklyn Museum in 1968, there is an transcript prepared by the Archives of American Art in 1969, and a photocopy of the 1969 transcript with handwritten corrections.)
    - Excerpt, 1968, (1 sound tape reel)
  - Steven Lang (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Original Interview, 1967 June 15, (2 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1967
  - Robert Laurent (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Original Interview, 1966 July 6, (1 sound tape reel)
    - Transcript, 1966
  - Jacob Lawrence (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Original Interview, 1968 March 21, (2 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1968
  - Jack Levine (Box 4, Folder 15-16)
    - Original Interview, 1965 February 24, (1 sound tape reel)
    - Transcript, 1965
    - Original Interview, 1968 February 6, (2 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1968
  - Jack Levine (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Excerpt, 1968
  - Jacques Lipchitz (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Original Interview, 1965 April 27, (1 sound tape reel)
    - Transcript, 1965
  - Seymour Lipton (Box 5, Folder 3-4)
    - Original Interview, 1966 May 20, (2 sound tape reels)
    - Excerpt, 1968, (1 sound tape reel)
  - Boris Margo (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Original Interview, 1968 March 21, (1 sound tape reel)
    - Transcript, 1968
  - Ursula Meyer (Box 5, Folder 6-7)
    - Original Interview, 1968 February 24, (2 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1968
    - Excerpts, 1968, (2 sound tape reels)
  - Hans Moller (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Original Interview, 1965 May 3, (1 sound tape reel)
    - Transcript, 1965
  - Walter Murch (Box 5, Folder 9-12)
    - Original Interview, between 1965 and 1967, (5 sound tape reels)
    - Excerpt, 1968, (1 sound tape reel)
    - Retrospective Exhibition Acoustiguide 1967, (1 sound tape reel)
    - Retrospective Exhibition Acoustiguide Transcript, 1967
  - Louise Nevelson (Box 5, Folder 13-14)
    - Original Interview, 1965 May 3, (2 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1965
    - Excerpt, 1968, (1 sound tape reel)
  - Toshio Odate (Box 5, Folder 15-16)
    - Original Interview, 1968 January 19, (3 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1968
    - Excerpt, 1968, (1 sound tape reel)
  - Elliot Offner (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Original Interview, 1966 September 22, (2 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1966
  - Douglas Ohlson (Box 6, Folder 2-3)
    - Original Interview, 1968 February 15, (3 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1968
  - Kenzo Okada (Box 6, Folder 4-5)
    - Original Interview, 1966 December 14, (2 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1966
    - Excerpt, 1968, (1 sound tape reel)
  - Amanda Palmer (Box 6, Folder 6-7)
    - Original Interview, 1968 February 16
    - Transcript, 1968
    - Excerpt, 1968
  - Irene Rice Periera (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Original Interview, 1966 July 26, (1 sound tape reel)
    - Transcript, 1966
  - Gabor Peterdi (Box 6, Folder 9-10)
    - Original Interview, 1966 July 5, (2 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1966
    - Excerpt, 1968, (1 sound tape reel)
  - Ad Reinhardt (Box 6, Folder 11-13)
    - Original Interview, 1967 June 14, (4 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1967
    - Excerpt, 1968, (1 sound tape reel)
  - Bill Richards (Box 6, Folder 14-15)
    - Original Interview, 1968 March 15, (2 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1968
    - Excerpt, 1968, (1 sound tape reels)
  - Larry Rivers (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Original Interview, 1966 June 8, (1 sound tape reel)
    - Transcript, 1966
    - Excerpt, 1968, (1 sound tape reel)
  - Emilio Sanchez (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Original Interview, 1967 June 22, (2 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1967
  - Karl Schrag (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Original Interview, 1966 May 20, (1 sound tape reel)
    - Transcript, 1966
  - Ben Shahn (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Original Interview, 1966 May 26, (1 sound tape reel)
    - Transcript, 1966
  - Charles Sheeler (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Original Interview, 1965 April 27, (2 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1965
  - Aaron Sopher (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Original Interview, 1965 April 20, (1 sound tape reel)
    - Transcript, 1965
  - Moses Soyer (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Original Interview, 1966 June 8, (2 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1966
  - Raphael Soyer (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Original Interview, 1966 June 10, (2 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1966
  - William Thon (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Original Interview, 1966 April 11, (1 sound tape reel)
    - Transcript, 1966
  - Elbert Weinberg (Box 7, Folder 10-11)
    - Original Interview, 1966 November 15, (2 sound tape reels)
    - Monologue on "Temptation of Eve," Original Interview, circa 1966, (1 sound cassette)
    - Monologue on "Temptation of Eve," Transcript, circa 1966
  - William and Marguerite Zorach (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Original Interview, 1965 May 18, (2 sound tape reels)
    - Transcript, 1965